OK, so welcome back, everyone.
Today, we'll go
more into circuits
as you did yesterday in
the afternoon session.
Just this time, it's going to
be circuits with extra features.
On top of them are more
specialized circuits.
So we'll start with
synaptic plasticity
in reinforcement learning.
So in other words, we
will model circuits
with learning rules or synaptic
plasticity rules in them that
adapt over time.
Now, the synaptic
plasticity in general
is the adaptations that
happen within synapses.
And as we saw yesterday
morning, synapses
is how neurons communicate
with one another.
So when we say that one synapse
is potentiated or becomes
strengthened, then
it is more it's
easier for a presynaptic
neuron to communicate spikes
to a postsynaptic one.
And likewise, depression
or weakening the synapse
is the opposite of this.
And we can have different
synaptic mechanisms working
on different timescales
within the brain,
from milliseconds to
even minutes and longer.
And a very classic rule
about synaptic plasticity,
you probably have heard of this,
but put forth by Donald Hebb
in the '40s about neurons that
fire together, wire together,
which, in other words, means
that if the spike times of two
neurons are very close to one
another and these neurons are
connected, of course,
with the synapse,
then the synapse would
get strengthened.
And we will see essentially
different flavors
of this Hebbian rule
today in the exercises.
So you have seen this
the corticostriatal model
in the first day's talk,
and partial view of that you
have built yesterday.
And essentially, this
model was originally
designed to do
category learning.
And as you might remember, the
task with category learning
was originating in the macaque
literature, where, essentially,
the monkey had to decide whether
a specific dot pattern, so
a cue like this one, belongs to
category left or category right.
And these are the two prototypes
where that essentially
generated all the stimuli.
Of course, the monkey had
never seen the prototypes,
but the challenge was to come up
with a categorization rule that
can distinguish
between these things.
So every stimulus here, I
should say, is an exemplar.
And this is a distorted image
of either one of the two
prototypes.
So the animals never see
exactly the prototype.
So, yeah, the animal has
never seen the prototype.
Just by trial and error and
taking actions and receiving
feedback, it has to learn how
to distinguish between the two
categories.
And this, we claim,
is essentially
driven by synaptic plasticity
in the animal's brain.
And this is what the full
corticostriatal model building
neuron blocks has in it as well.
So here, I'm just showing
you the model again, just
to remind you of the
structure and also highlight
a few components which
have to do with the task.
So the stimulus coming
into the model, this
is [INAUDIBLE] stimulus.
You build [INAUDIBLE]
stimuli yesterday.
So these are the dot patterns
coming in to visual cortex.
And after the cortex to
the striatum connections
and to other
subcortical regions,
we have the final action,
which is the saccade
because the monkey chooses
left or right by looking
at the left or right direction.
And after the action, we also
have the behavioral feedback,
which is reward or
no reward according
to the other choice made.
So these are all part of the
model, so within your block's
model actual behavioral
tasks, and link them
to a circuit model
with no problem.
And as I mentioned
yesterday as well,
this model was
built on principles
about structure and function
that we have about the brain.
And it was constrained
by specific parameters
that we got from the literature.
It was never directly fitted
to data from this task.
Yet it can match both the
physiological elements
of the task, as you can see
here, in the [INAUDIBLE]
LFB and its spectrogram.
And also, it can match the
learning behavior over time.
And it can actually match
both the [INAUDIBLE]
phase and the behavior
because of the learning rules
that help it adapt over trials.
And this model includes both
LTP, Long-Term Potentiation,
in the corticocortical
synapses, that
is, the synapses between the
visual cortex and the anterior
cortex.
And it also includes
corticostriatal synapses
that can do both LTP or LTD.
And these are also modulated by
dopamine between the anterior
cortex and the striatum here.
And we'll get into more
detail about these.
And as a note in your blogs, we
call this units synaptic rules,
learning rules
because this is all
in the context of
decision-making.
So the learning rule is
essentially the gradient
that the synaptic weights
follow to adapt over time.
So first with the
corticocortical LTP,
this is a form of Hebbian
learning, as you can see here
with this term, the LTP.
The S's here are
the activities of
the presynaptic and
postsynaptic neuron.
And it also includes
an extra reversal term,
which essentially means
that this term is actually
dependent on dopamine
released in VTA.
So what's happening here
is that, during the trial,
there is potentiation
happening in the synapses,
in the corticocortical
synapses, but in anticipation
for the result, for the reward.
But maybe if the choice that
the animal makes is wrong,
then there is
actually a reversal
of that potentiation
mediated by this term
here, which happens
through dopamine VTA
because whether there the
animal receives a reward
or not actually drives the
dopamine release in VTA, which,
in turn, drives this
reversal or no reversal.
So here, you can see
an example of how
this plasticity rule drives
the weight changes over trials.
So here, we have simulated
700 trials of the task.
Each trial is a separate
stimulus and one action and one
reward feedback.
And as you can see, this
is an adjacency matrix
for the weights between the
visual cortex and the anterior
cortex.
And you can see the weight value
is changing from the beginning
to the end of the task.
And likewise, you can
see the average weight
in these same synapses
actually adapting over time
and reaching a stable value.
So moving on to the second
place, where we have implemented
synaptic plasticity
in this model, that
is the connections from the
anterior cortex to the striatum,
so these connections follow a
more sophisticated rule which
can induce both LTP and LTD.
And essentially,
this rule, again,
the changes in weight,
the weight gradient.
In other words, it has the
typical Hebbian-like component
where it is a function
of the activities
of the presynaptic and
postsynaptic neuron.
But now, this
Hebbian component is
modulated by the DA,
the dopamine, released
in the substantia nigra.
So essentially, here,
we have a third region,
this S and C working as a
modulator in the connections
between cortex and striatum.
And there is also
a third term, which
actually depends on the current
values of these weights.
And as I was saying before,
because of this immediate tie
to dopamine, any reward
feedback can actually
either strengthen the
synapses or punishment
or omission of reward can
also weaken the synapses
and induce LTP.
And also, this rule,
you can work out
the math, which actually you can
see in more detail in this paper
as well.
If you expand on the
dopamine term, which
is essentially dopamine
released in S and C,
it has some baseline dopamine
plus this epsilon value.
And this epsilon
value is, essentially,
the difference between
the actual reward
received and the expected value
of the reward to be received.
And this difference shows
up in classic reinforcement
learning tools like Q-learning.
Or even in temporal
difference learning as well,
you can see a flavor of
this plus some extra terms.
So this is a nice result
that highlights the fact
that simpler agent
models can actually
relate to neurobiology through
this synaptic plasticity rule.
And here you can
see a result, which
is a hyperparameter search over
having two different parameter
sets.
You can see, in fact, how
varying this, essentially,
this prediction error, which
is the epsilon, the difference
between actual value
and predicted value.
How does this affect the weight
gradient, the delta of the W
here?
And how this can reduce both
depression and potentiation
according-- based on the
science, essentially,
of the prediction error.
So what we will
build here is, again,
a partial view of the
full model in two places.
Initially, we'll work on a
model like the second model
from yesterday, so two cortical
regions, a [INAUDIBLE] stimulus
and an ascending system that
modulates their activity.
And we will see how
Hebbian plasticity
works with no feedback.
So we will remove the LTP.
There's no LTP reversal
because we'll just
let the system simulate
and see how it adapts.
And in the second example, we
will include a striatum elements
as well.
And in this case, I will
do proper reinforcement
learning with--
18 months, we'll
have a category.
There are correct-labeled
categories.
And the model will have to
make a decision on each trial.
And we will judge whether
the decision is good or bad
and then adapt the
weights accordingly.
And you will see how this works.
So, yeah, this was all.
So you can navigate to
the synaptic plasticity
and reinforcement
learning notebook.
And again, feel free to
ask us any questions.